<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A receyt to stay the plague. Deliuered in a sermon by R.W. minister of Gods Word</title>
            <author>Wright, Robert, d. 1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15771</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26037A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1564:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A receyt to stay the plague. Deliuered in a sermon by R.W. minister of Gods Word</title>
                  <author>Wright, Robert, d. 1626.</author>
                  <author>T. R., minister.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. N[orton] and are to be sold by Robert Bird, at his shop in Cheap-side, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.W. = Robert Wright.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Another edition, with new preface by T.R., minister, of STC 26037.</note>
                  <note>A variant copy has the title page in an early state, without the quotation from Numb. xvi.46, and with the misprint "Rird" in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Plague --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12044:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12044:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RECEYT TO STAY THE PLAGVE. Deliuered in a Sermon by <hi>R. W.</hi> Miniſter of Gods word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>I. N.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Robert Rird,</hi> at his ſhop in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Bible.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12044:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12044:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader (whether <hi>Citizen</hi> or <hi>Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man</hi>) the Title of this ſermon, (A Receit to ſtay the Plague,) may aquaint you with the ſcope of the Author. A ſubiect as I conceiue fit for this time wherein the hand of God is more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon vs, threatning death and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by this diſeaſe of the Plague. And as in all diſeaſes ſo in this, the cauſe being taken away, the Effect ceaſeth. To worke this Cure, the Author hath taken the ſame method, as in the view of this his inſuewing labour will appeare, The approbation of it when it was preached by a Religious and Learned Miniſter, an intire friend of mine on the like occaſion that it is now printed, Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the coueniency of it at this time and the Chriſtian like deſire, that I a poore
<pb facs="tcp:12044:3"/> fellow Miniſter ſuruiuing him haue to doe good, hath Imboldned mee to further the publiſhing of it, conceiuing that the generall mortality both in Citty and Country will require pardon of this my boldnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the iſſue to God, and heartily deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our mutuall prayers for a good ſucceſſe of this <hi>Receit.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By an vnworthy Miniſter of the Goſpell. <hi>T. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12044:3"/>
            <head>A RECEIT TO STAY THE PLAGVE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>NVME. 16. part of verſe. 46.</bibl>
                  <p>Goe quickely vnto the Congregation, and make an attonement for them, for there is Wrath gone out from the Lord; the Plague is begunne.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ought to bee the care of a faithfull Steward ouer the Houſholde of GOD, that they haue their meat giuen them, not onely <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in their iuſt proportion and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in their due time and ſeaſon, <hi>Lucke.</hi> 12.42. which was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> rule to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that the food mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to the people of God, ſhould be both ſeaſoned and ſeſonable, a poynt not onely of Good learning, but of good diſcretion, <hi>to haue a word in time for him that is weary, Eſa.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12044:4"/> 50.4. Which practiſe in the Miniſter of God, is the true following of the Apoſtles counſell, <hi>Apply your ſelues to the time, Rom.</hi> 12.11. Not that they ſhould be men-pleaſers, or time-ſeruers, but to apply themſelues to the time, in the occurrents and occaſions thereof. In due conſideration whereof, being by Gods bleſſings enabled againe to ſpeake vnto you, there could not bee a fitter Scripture for you to heare, or me to diſcourſe of, then this that I haue read. The calamity of the times, the meaſure of our ſinnes, the wrath of God, the ſeuerity of his punniſhment, all calling vpon vs, <hi>to goe quickly to the congregation and make an attonement, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two maine ſinnes in the former part of this Chapter that prouoked the wrath of the Lord againſt his people: the firſt was an open rebellion of the faction of <hi>Corah,</hi> and his confederates in the 1.2.3. <hi>verſes, &amp;c.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, a generall murmer of all the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>Moſes and Aron,</hi> Gods Magiſtrate and Gods Miniſter, <hi>ver.</hi> 41. The former was punniſhed by an example of Iuſtice without an example; they and all theirs went quicke into the graue, <hi>verſ.</hi> 33. The latter came vnto ſuch a prouocation, by their adding ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne, that the Lord threatned to conſume the whole Congregation in a moment with a fearefull plague, <hi>verſe</hi> 45. To preuent which, and by ſome meanes to abate at leaſt the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12044:4"/> edge of Gods fury, <hi>Moſes</hi> giues this ſudden, but ſafeſt aduice to <hi>Aaron,</hi> to take a Cenſer, and to put fire therein from the Altar, and to put on Incence, and then <hi>to get him quickly to the congregation, and to make an attonement, &amp;c.</hi> So that, the text you haue heard, is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, or a medicine for a fearefull maladie; Phiſicke for the Plague. Which firſt, muſt bee taken with all ſpeed that may bee; for the diſeaſe is deſperate, and therefore <hi>Sine mora, Goe quickly.</hi> Secondly, the place where, is in the <hi>Congregation.</hi> Thirdly, the Medicine it ſelfe, is a precious <hi>Oyntment,</hi> and Playſter of <hi>Attonement.</hi> Fourthly, a principall Actor in miniſtring the phiſicke, is <hi>the Prieſt.</hi> Fiftly the motiue wherefore, to appeaſe the wrath of the Lord, gone our againſt the people. Laſtly, the meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that wrath was executed, <hi>the Plague was begunne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole then being an aduiſe of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> the Magiſtrate to <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares euen in the very entrance of this Scripture, that contrary to the principles and poſitions of Ieſuitiſme, Magiſtrates haue power to giue Order for the Worſhip and Seruice of God; and that the Prince of the people is <hi>Cuſtos vtriuſque Tabulae, Deu.</hi> 17.18 The Booke of the Law ſhall remaine with the King. So that the King hath power not onely to command in Ciuill Affaires, but in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12044:5"/> matters concerning Diuine Religion; So did <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſo did <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſo did <hi>Ezechias,</hi> ſo did <hi>Ioſias,</hi> and ſo did the King of <hi>Niniue</hi> in a caſe of Gods wrath pronounced againſt the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Proclaime a Faſt. Ioel.</hi> 3.7. So did the Chriſtian Emperours in former time. So did <hi>Moſes</hi> heere, as a chiefe Magiſtrate, giue order for a publicke worke of Religion to be done in the publicke Congregation. Againe on the other ſide, howſoeuer we learne, this is a worke fitting to be done in caſes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity; yet in that <hi>Aaron</hi> doth it not, but by order firſt preſcribed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> it croſſeth the preſumption of their zeale, and the affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſingularity in any priuate man, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular Congregation, that ſhall runne before a State, and preuent them in their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that may concerne the common cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of a Country, or a City, for vvhich God is to be pacified, and the Land purged in generall, when as the Gouernors in their places are farre more wiſer then any priuate man, to know the danger, and without doubt, may be preſumed to be as zealous in the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt time to apply the remedy. Therefore, whatſoeuer euery priuate man is bound to doe betwixt himſelfe and his owne ſoule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt himſelfe and his owne Family, (as bound he is) by his prayers and his penitence to auert the wrath of God already gone out againſt the ſinnes of a Nation: yet I find no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12044:5"/> vvarrant for any to take vpon them to gather any Congregation, to ſanctifie a publicke Faſt or to call vnto mourning, before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate hath giuen order for it. But that once done, vve finde heere, and that in expreſſe tearmes, that it muſt be done quickly; <hi>Goe quickly vnto the congregation, and make an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for them. Agree with thine aduerſary quickly, Mat.</hi> 5.26. <hi>while thou art in the way, before thou come vnto the Iudge.</hi> If God once be an aduerſary, <hi>agree quickly.</hi> It is ſo with men, much more ought it to be ſo vvith God; giue all dilligence to bee reconciled vnto God. <hi>Mora trahit periculum,</hi> delay breedes danger; he that is not fit to day, vvill be leſſe fit to morrow, and no man knoweth vvhat to morrow day ſhall be, if it be not done before the hand ſtrike vs to death. It is not then a temporall, but an eternall plague: for heereafter there is no hope of helpe. Delay is one of the Deuils moſt dangerous aſſaults, vvhereby he gets too much aduantage of the ſoules of men, vvhile they dally vvith Gods iudgements: and therefore <hi>Hodie, To day if you will heare his voice, harden not your hearts:</hi> yet a little while is the day with you, the night commeth vvhen no man vvorketh. <hi>Seeke the Lord while hee may bee found, call vpon him while hee is neere, Eſa.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Now is the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, now is the day of ſaluation,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. The time is now ours, vve haue right in it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12044:6"/> that which is to come, is the Lords, to iudge the miſ-ſpending of this, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 10.6. The Angell ſweares by him that liueth for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that time ſhall be no more; that is, after this time, no more time for repentance, no more time for attonement: therefore doe that you ought to doe for your owne good quickly.</p>
            <p>This day, this houre, this time, Now there is roome, there will be none hereafter. It will bee too late to knocke with the ſilly Virgins, when the doore is ſhut, <hi>Goe quickly.</hi> They haue a rule in ſauing pollicie for auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Plague, and it conſiſts in three words, <hi>Citò, Longè, Tardè:</hi> Goe quickly, Goe farre enough, Make no haſte to returne. I would we would be perſwaded to vſe them not in ſauing Pollicie, but in ſauing Piety.</p>
            <p>And firſt to begin with <hi>Citò,</hi> for that I find in the Text a rule preſcribed by the Holy Ghoſt, to flie vnto God quickly, not from him: for alas whither ſhall a man flie from him; the wings of the morning are too ſlow, the bottome of the depth is too ſhallow; the fathermoſt part of the earth is too neere to keepe vs from him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Longè,</hi> for that implyed in the attonement, not farre from his Iuſtice, ſeeing it is to ſwift for vs, and will ſoone ouertake vs whereſoeuer; but farre from our ſinnes, that haue called out his Iuſtice, that by our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12044:6"/> repentance and amendment we may ſtay the courſe of it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Tardè;</hi> that is not to returne in haſt to our ſinnes againe; for ſinnes returned vnto, prouoke a worſe iudgement: <hi>Sinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee,</hi> was the after dyet that hee gaue vnto the ſicke man, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14. The tree that is twiſe dead, is neere vnto curſing: No Leper in Scripture is twice cleanſed; no Prodigall is twice receiued; no loſt Sheepe is twice brought home; no dead man is twiſe raiſed, no Deuill is twiſe caſt out. The relaps of ſickneſſe is dangerous, but the relaps of ſinne is more dangerous: <hi>Goe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God, goe farre from ſinne, make no haſt to ſinne againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goe quickly to the Congregation.</hi> That's the next circumſtance, the place where: for albeit euery man ſhould endeauour in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret cloſet to reconcile himſelfe vnto God, and to <hi>commune with his owne heart,</hi> euen in his Bed-chamber, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> aduiſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. yet where all men are ſinners, and the hand of Gods wrath ſeemeth to bee ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out in generall, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, age or degree: All men are bound to one and the ſame worke, that with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and one act the Lord might bee intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>whole Congregation.</hi> For howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Lord is well pleaſed with euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mans ſeruice in prauate; yet that which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12044:7"/> hee ſhall doe in publicke, is <hi>de meliore bono,</hi> and much more acceptable. There was a Law made for it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12,5. <hi>In that place which the Lord your God ſhal chuſe amongſt all the Tribes, to ſet his Name in in that his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation you ſhall ſeeke vnto him.</hi> Neither was this a Law Iudicicall, or Ceremoniall, that bound the Iewe <hi>onely for a time;</hi> but morall and perpetuall, that binds the Chriſtian for euer: nor was it a Law for the Iewiſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue onely, wherein they taught and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp their Incenſe, Sacrifice, and Oblations on the Sabbath dayes, but for the Temple vnder the profeſſion of the Goſpell alſo; that as God is to be praiſed in the great Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſo he was to be pacified in the great Congregation. Therefore as the Prophet ſaid well, <hi>I will praiſe thee, O Lord, in the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in much people will I giue thankes vnto thee, Pſal.</hi> 35.18. So <hi>Moſes</hi> did here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe as well, that what <hi>Aaron</hi> did herein, he ſhould doe it in the Congregation.</p>
            <p>In the baniſhment of the Iſaraelites by the waters of Babylon, where they ſate and wept, Ieruſalem vvas vowed to be their chiefeſt ioy; not for any other thing, but that there they might <hi>worſhip the Lord in his holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in the Congregation of his Seruants.</hi> And vvhen Chriſt gaue the promiſe to two or three, it is euident, that he intended not priuate meetings, ſo much as publicke Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12044:7"/> in the Church, as appeareth by the connexion of the Text; <hi>Et ero vobiſcum vſque ad confirmationem ſaeculi, Mat.</hi> 28.20. Is a promiſe to the Aſſembly in the Church, where vvith one mind, and one mouth, God may be ſerued &amp; glorified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6. vvhich vvas the Apoſtles exhortation, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.21. That praiſes might be giuen in the Church through Ieſus Chriſt <hi>vnto all generations for euer.</hi> So that the fitneſſe of place hath heere in <hi>Moſes</hi> direction a good correſpondence vvith the fitneſſe of time, as moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, and moſt apt for men to make their attonement in. And therein vve fall vpon the third Branch, the <hi>Medicine for the malady, Goe quickly vnto the Congregation, and make an attonement for them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vvhole need not the Phiſician, ſaith Chriſt but the ſicke. Theſe people were ſicke, and ſicke vnto death; the vvay to cure them, vvas to make an attonement for them; the manner how it vvas to be done, vvas by offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp Incenſe; vvhich albeit, it vvere a ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall action, yet vvas it alwayes ioyned vvith a religious acte of deuotion in prayer and penitence. To vvhich purpoſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet prayeth, <hi>Let my prayer be ſet before thee as incenſe, Pſal.</hi> 145.2. And indeed it is a moſt apt reſemblance: for as the vſe of Inſenſe vvas to ſweeten that vvhich vvas vnſauory; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo the vvicked thoughts of our hearts,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12044:8"/> and the vncleane actions of our liues, which yeeld an vnſauory ſmell in the noſthrils of the Lord are ſweetned by no other meanes, but by the Incenſe of our prayers: therefore to ſhew how the one is reſembled by the other, it is ſaid, that while the Incenſe was in bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the people were without at their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Luke,</hi> 1.10. And in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 8.3. the ſweet odours that were offered in the golden Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, were offered with the Prayers of the Saints.</p>
            <p>So that the firſt Ingredience for the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, was prayer; but not prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: For as <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> came not to Chriſt with the Boxe of precious Oyntment and ſweet perfume onely; but ſhee brought withall a ſorrowfull heart, and penitent teares for the ſinne of her Soule. So to the action of prayer muſt bee ioyned the worke of penitence: for ſuch was the practiſe of Gods people euer. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.3. The Arke of the Lord being taken by the Phyliſtines, the Prophets exhorts them to repent, and turne vnto God, and hee would deliuer them; and the euent prooued the promiſe to bee true. Which example, albeit it concerne a caſe of warre, and ſo not improper for our times, yet the practiſe may ſerue as well for this of ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame Order did <hi>Daniel</hi> obſerue, in the Attonement that he made with GOD,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12044:8"/> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.5.6. Together with their prayers, there is the acknowledgment of their ſinnes; <hi>We haue finned, and haue committed iniquity, and haue done wickedly; yea, rebelled, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thy precepts, and thy iudgements.</hi> And then he ſhewes wherein: <hi>For wee would not obey thy ſeruauts the Prophets, which ſpake in thy name, to our Kings, to our Princes, to our Fathers, and to all the people of the Land.</hi> Wherein he confeſſeth that euery one had ſinned, accuſing all, excepting none, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of ſinners, and of ſin, and therefore all had need of attonement in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; albeit, no doubt of it, but ſome had offended more grieuouſly then other ſome: yet <hi>all were guilty.</hi> So the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all the Inhabitants of the Land into the <hi>Houſe of the Lord, to offer vp their prayers</hi> and their Penitence, <hi>Ioel.</hi> 1.14. Without which no maruell it is, that there can be no attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that God doth ſtill keepe man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>with his heauy hand, Iam.</hi> 4.2. In another calamity, he ſaith, You fight, and you warre, and you get nothing; Whats the reaſon? Becauſe you aske not, thats <hi>primus error,</hi> the firſt defect. Againe, you aske, and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not, why ſo? <hi>becauſe you aske amiſſe,</hi> thats the next defect; there wants ſomewhat to their prayers, <hi>to make vp their attouement.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in his fourth Chapter, ſpeakes plainely to the poynt, <hi>That euen the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12044:9"/> prayers of the moſt godly are not aproued of God</hi> vnleſſe they for whom they pray <hi>doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> Although <hi>Noah, Daniell,</hi> and <hi>Iob,</hi> theſe three men ſtood vp, <hi>yet ſhall they onely ſaue their owne ſoules in their righteouſneſſe.</hi> So ſaith God <hi>Iere.</hi> 15. <hi>If Moſes and Samuel were before me, I would not yet regard this people.</hi> So that for the Act of attonement, albeit the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the faithfull are powerfull, yet are they not ſo powerfull as to releeue impenitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; therefore did <hi>God, Iere.</hi> 7. borbid the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet expreſſely not to pray for the Iſraelites: <hi>Pray not for this people, neither lift thou vp thy voyce for them.</hi> So God reiected the prayers of <hi>Samuel</hi> for <hi>Saul.</hi> Vpon which followeth this concluſion; That if the penitence of the people be not ioyned with the prayers of the Prieſt, the attonement will not be made, and ſo wee muſt conſider of the perſon of the Prieſt, and no otherwiſe. Which is the fourth circumſtance obſerued, that although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> principall Agent to offer vp the Incenſe of prayer for the people; yet not hee onely for them, but they with him, and for themſelues, muſt deſire the Lord not to correct in his wrath according to their ſinnes, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them according <hi>to his owne goodneſſe</hi> True it is, that the Commiſſion is deliuered here to <hi>Aron,</hi> but the Congregation were to ioyne with him in the execution. The Miniſter of God is a principall man ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12044:9"/> and ſet a part for the execution of the will of <hi>God, the declaration of his word;</hi> the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>obedience,</hi> and all <hi>religious actions.</hi> But all the burden of Gods ſeruice doth not lye vpon him; and therefore the wiſdome of our Church did well ordaine that in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, the Miniſter ſhould not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all; But that the people ſhould ioyne in the open confeſſion of their ſinnes, and in the prayers for remiſſion, or at the leaſt, ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to euery ſacrifice of Prayer, and of prayſe performed in the Congregation; and yet though they were tyed to this, ſtill the chiefe care and duty lyeth vpon the Miniſter, nor muſt hee bee defectiue, whatſoeuer the people be; but ſay as good <hi>Samuel</hi> ſayd, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould ſinne againſt the Lord, in ceaſing to pray for yon.</hi> And ſo much in one word may ſuffice for the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the perſon. Now followeth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>For there is wrath gone out from the Lord the Plague is begun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſuch a caſe as this was, the firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall thing that is to be ſought out, is to enquire into the Cauſe that brings it on. The cauſe in this chapter as you haue partly heard, was an iniury offered vnto the Prieſthood, and the preſumption of <hi>Corah</hi> in vilifying both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron.</hi> I take no pleaſure in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſinne by way of compariſon: I onely pray that the Sacriledge of this City bee not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12044:10"/> the principall ſinne layd to their charge in this Plague: We haue heard enough, if any thing he enough. God giue vnderſtanding hearts to apply, and to lay the finger vpon the right ſoare. For too ſure we are <hi>the wrath of the Lord is gone out.</hi> The Iudgements of God for ſinne, and againſt ſinners, as they are many in number, and diuers in kind, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſecret, ſometimes open, ſo they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer iuſt and vpon good cauſe. <hi>Oculta multa, iniuſta nulla,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to too many are to ſeeke for the true <hi>cauſe</hi> as well as for the <hi>conſideration of the perſon</hi> from whom <hi>Iudgement</hi> commeth, making ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euery thing then their owne ſinnes; and euery cauſe in the courſe of nature, then the <hi>God of Nature,</hi> and the cauſe of all cauſes the Author of their puniſhment: Whereof it comes to paſſe, that men thinke all iudgments to be ordinary, and none extraordinary, or to be the rodd of Gods Vengeance wherewith he puniſheth ſinners, and ſo neuer apply the <hi>puniſhment</hi> either to themſelues, or their ſinne or once <hi>caſt vp an eye to the Lord that punni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth:</hi> Where as indeed two things are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to be conſidered in any Epidemicall diſeaſe or publicke miſery.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the cauſe wherefore, and then the hand that ſmiteth. Wherein the iudgement of the World that lookes all to ſecond cauſes rather then the firſt, and principall, is ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12044:10"/> fowly corrupted, that men know not well, either where to aske counſell, or how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues being ſurpriſed with any danger; taking ſtill the wrong cauſe for the right, and the ſecond for the firſt. Whereas the true cauſe is the corruption of manners that corrupts our bodies, and rottenneſſe in ſinne that brings rottenneſſe in the fleſh. But as the Phyſition for the body hitting vpon the right cauſe of the diſeaſe, doth with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudgement and happier ſucceſſe, cure his <hi>Patient.</hi> So we, when we ſhall finde the true cauſe of Gods wrath, ſhall the better know what to doe in that affliction, and how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid it; Wherein the firſt thing to be done is to looke into the Motiue that called out wrath, and then vnto the hand that doth <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it.</hi> For the firſt, that ſinne is the maine cauſe of Gods diſpleaſure, it needs no farther ſearch then the guilt of our owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and the iniquity of the times beyond meaſure ſinnefull: So that the wrath of God is reuealed from Heauen againſt the <hi>vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and vnrighteonſnes of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18 Its not this or that Coniunction of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, or the ſundry Ecclipſes of the Sunne and the Moone that wiſards fondly immagine; but the Lord of heauen and of heauenly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of the earth and all that therein is, that ſo draweth the ſword of his wrath, that the very ayre, and breath of our life ſhall be our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12044:11"/> poyſon for the ſinne of the Soule; and where he is not preuented, and that quickly with an earneſt inuocatiou of his name, and vnfained repentance of our ſinnefull liues, The very dreggs of his wrath will be powred out, becauſe men are ſetled in the lees and dreggs of their ſinnes. Let not men then looke to the right hand or the left, and like the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> conceale their owne faults and lay them vpon others, but let them turne their eyes inward, and looke into the blots and ſtaines of their owne vncleaneneſſe; Search and trie their owne hearts, and they ſhall ſoone finde the cauſe of the breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and Man.</p>
            <p>The ſinne certaine of the firſt man, was the firſt breath; and euer ſince as ſinne hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and a bounded, ſo hath God and man bene ſeparated and diuided. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in the aboundance of his merecy he hath ſuch a regard of ſinnefull man, that he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled in the attonement made in his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne, and mans alone Sauiour: yet ſuch is the condition of his Iuſtice, that as his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy wants not abundant clemency; ſo the ſame wants not due ſeuerity: Nor can he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the thing that is euill; nor can his eyes that are pure eyes, behold any thing that is vncleane in it ſelfe, or by the blood of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanſed, but ſtill he pnnniſheth with iuſtice the ſinnes of the wicked. And though <hi>there
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12044:11"/> bee no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, Rom,</hi> 8.1. Yet there is correction due to ſuch as liue <hi>after the fleſh, ond not after the ſpirit:</hi> And though the blood of Chriſt were an Attonement ſufficient for all our ſinnes, and by his death hee appeaſeth his Fathers wrath, and payd the priſe of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: yet that blood of his left no liberty to build our ſinnes vpon his death; for that is ſucking of the blood of CHRIST to faſt, and turning the grace of God into wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For though God was reconciled vnto man by his Sonne, yet that reconciliation neuer reached ſo farre, as to make a peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>God and ſinne.</hi> True it is, that great ſinnes are forgiuen in the Attonement made betweene God and his Sonne in the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: yet doth hee punniſh euen ſmall ſinnes, ſtill in the ſonnes of men that are impenitent; and albeit his mercy doth alwayes flye and cry about his Throane, yet it doth not ſo cry, as that he can heare no other cry againſt vs. For the cry of our ſinnes will goe vp as here it did, and neuer feaſe crying in his eare for Iuſtice till they awake him, as it were out of the ſleepe of his long ſuffering and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Abels</hi> blood will cry againſt <hi>Carne, Gen.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinne of Adultery and Murder will call for Iuſtire, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>Geheſies</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption will draw on a Leprofie, 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 5. And the very Stone will cry out of the wall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12044:12"/> of Oppreſſion, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.11. So that howſoeuer for our comfort, he hath an eare of mercy for crying ſinners: yet to reſtraine our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and to keepe vs in awe that we ſinne not, he hath alſo an eare of Iuſtice <hi>for crying ſins;</hi> and no euill doth at any time befall vson't, it is the punniſhment of ſome ſinne; and whereas God doth many times forbeare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and like <hi>Ionathans</hi> Bow ſhoots ſhort of vs, or on the right hand, or the left, or beyond vs: yet that forbearance is no acquittance, but makes his punniſhment more grieuous when it comes. For as it is impoſſible but the all-ſeeing eye of God ſhould ſee the ſinnes of the Sonnes of men: ſo it is impoſſible that ſeeing in the end he ſhould not punniſh, and though it be certaine ſure that <hi>non niſi coactus percutit,</hi> he neuer ſtrickes but when he is vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and then <hi>Caſtigat nolenter,</hi> as <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> ſaith. Yet when hee is vrged, and our ſinnes force him therevnto, he will punniſh with a witneſſe, where men then haue made a couenant with Death and a league with Hell, its high time to make an <hi>Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with God, for if he once beginne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that he will ſurely make an end: And if his wrath be kindled, yea but a little, <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put there truſt in him, Pſal.</hi> 2.12. But if a great deale, then woe bee to all thoſe that prouoked him. His iudgements are not <hi>terriculamenta nutricum,</hi> Colluſions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12044:12"/> of Nurſes to keepe children in awe; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions of men abounding in ſinne. If the wrath of God faſten vpon vs but in this world we ſhall finde it like the Brand in <hi>Caines</hi> face, that cannot be rnbd out; like a botch or a blaine, that all the Balme in <hi>Gilead</hi> cannot cure: for its a fearefull thing to fall into the bandes of the angry God, and if his wrath be once gone out, its time to make haſt. For the word of <hi>his wrath</hi> in the courſe of the Scriptures is neuer vſed but in the full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of iniquity, and the full meaſure of his Iuſtice; For till the ſinnes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prouocation, and hardning of hearts; he neuer ſware in his wrath, <hi>that they ſhould not enter into his reſt, Pſal.</hi> 59. and the laſt verſe. Its the execution of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, which God himſelfe teſtifieth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.21. <hi>They haue prouoked me to anger with their vanities, but I will moue them: For fire is kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in my wrath, and ſhall burne vnto the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of Hell, and ſhall conſume the Earth with her increaſe: I will ſend plagues and beſtow my arrowes vpon them, they ſhall be conſumed with a bitter deſtruction.</hi> In a word, the terrour of Gods wrath is ſo terrible as no man can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, for <hi>who knoweth the power of his wrath, Pſal.</hi> 90.11. Whereby we ſee how great a danger it is for men, when his wrath is gone out againſt them, I ſay, when it is gone out: For though it be wrath, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12044:13"/> wrath of the Lord, yet ſo long as it is ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Omnipotency of his power, or the aboundant grace of his mercy ouerruling his Iuſtice, and ſo concealed from vs, or at the leaſt, not gone out againſt vs, the feare and the danger is the leſſe: But if it bee <hi>gone out,</hi> then its more then time to looke about. <hi>For if the pillers of heauen,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>tremble and quake at his reproofe, Iob.</hi> 26.11. What ſhall <hi>Sinners</hi> on earth doe? Its a great mercy of God that their is a ſuſpention of his Iuſtice, for it is his mercy that wee are not all conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: But if that mercy bee abuſed, then the wrath of the Lord is no longer reſtrained, but euen from heauen it ſelfe, from whence commeth the influence of all good bleſſings to the ſonnes of men, euen from thence ſhall his wrath be ſent forth: and when men poyſon the Ayre with ſinne, then God will poyſon men with the Ayre: and the very breath of one man ſhall bee the baine, infection, and death of another: which is not onely the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of his wrath, but the execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the laſt circumſtance in the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Plague is begun,</hi> and therein we ſhall doe well to enter into conſideration, not ſo much of the nature of the Punniſhment, as of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing to bee thought of in the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which is <hi>the hand that ſmiteth.</hi> Wherein howſoeuer naturall men ſeeke out naturall cauſes, as I haue ſaid; yet hee that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12044:13"/> ſauours of any Religion, cannot but ſay, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur Dei eſt,</hi> this is the hand of God, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo witneſſing of himſelfe, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 45 7. <hi>I am he euen I, which make peace, and create euill Malum paene,</hi> he meaneth, the euill of punniſhment, naturall cauſes, being no cauſes, but onely meanes which God vſeth to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice the ſinnes of men, hee being the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and the efficient of all iudgements. The Scripture is both plentifull and plaine, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in direct words; That as all punniſhment comes from God, ſo this of the plague eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, and therefore the Prophet prayed, <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 39.11. <hi>Take away thy Plague from me; for I am euen conſumed by meanes of thy heauy hand.</hi> And King <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledgeth in his choyſe that the punniſhment of the <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> comes from the immediate hand of God: So the Scripture calles it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.3. <hi>The Sword of the Lord,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. <hi>And the Arrowes of his vengeance, Pſalme.</hi> 91.5. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men coeleſte,</hi> the Thunderbolts of heauen, and <hi>Bellum Dei contra homines,</hi> as ſome doe call it no ordinary iudgement: The reaſon, becauſe the ſinnes that call for it are no ordinary ſins. For as the ſinne here was no ordinary ſinne; So if the ſinnes of our age though they be too common, are no common ſinnes, but equall, if not tranſcend that of <hi>Corah,</hi> and his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, of which at large in the former part of this Chapter. VVho can thinke that a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12044:14"/> common death is a ſufficient punniſhment, and not rather looke that the earth ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen her mouth and ſwallow vp the offenders aliue; <hi>and they goe downe quicke into the pit,</hi> as in the 30. verſe. This Generation of ours, being too obdurate, and hard harted to be moued with ordinary iudgements. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Lord is forced extraordinarily to punniſh, and as it were immediately by his owne hands. <hi>For it is he that doth caſt into the bed of ſickneſſe. Reucl.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Iob</hi> the exact pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of patience, and mirrour of Affliction, looked farther and vnto higher matter, then Winde, and ayre, ſtorme and tempeſt, the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beans,</hi> or Satan himſelfe; and ſaid, <hi>Dominus dedit, Dominus abſtulit.</hi> So that we muſt learne not like beaſts, to looke after the Stone but after the right arme that threw it, and not ſo much to ſeeke to flye the perſons and the places infected, as their owne ſinnes which ſuch an infection followeth.</p>
            <p>For when men haue done what they can doe, either to preuent it before it come, or to cure it when its come; and the careful prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Magiſtrate is approoued good, and euery ſeuerall mans care not without good cauſe: yet its the Lord that muſt bleſſe the meanes of our ſafeguard: and that hee may bleſſe, let men ſay what they will, there is no ſuch Phyſicke as <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Penitence,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make an <hi>Attonement betweene God and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12044:14"/> our ſinnes.</hi> For as God will be knowne in his Iuſtice, ſo he will be knowne in his Mercy; and hee will heare them <hi>that call vpon him faithfully.</hi> For it is the grace of his mercy, and the mercy of his grace, that farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the grace of Herbes and Drugges, all the vertue of Simples and Compounds in the World, for the cure of thoſe Soares that Sinne doth make. To the obtaining whereof, Let vs quickly, euery man for himſelfe, and all, one for another flye vnto the Lord of mercy, by the feruent Deuotion of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; Let vs deſire the Lord to turne our hearts vnto him, that he may turne his Plague from vs; That vnto our <hi>Prayers</hi> wee may ioyne our <hi>Penitence,</hi> and with our <hi>Penitence,</hi> the amendment of our liues, that wee may thereby enter into a ſerious Meditation of our owne ſinnes, that haue prouoked his <hi>Wrath;</hi> and of his wrath that doth punniſh our ſinnes; acknowleging, and that feelingly, that the things that we ſuffer, are moſt iuſtly due to the ſinnes that we haue committed: ſeeing hee that ſuffers moſt, cannot ſuffer ſo much as he doth deſerue.</p>
            <p>In one word, let vs deſire the Lord of all mercy, to be mercifull vnto vs, and to giue vs grace to ſtay the courſe of our ſinning, that he may withall ſtay the hand of his punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. That albeit he haue begunne, yet that he would goe no farther, but ſay it is enough.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12044:15"/> That among all the bleſſing and fauours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon this Church, vpon our moſt Noble King, vpon his right worthy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, the whole State and his people, hee ſuffer not the meaſure of his Iuſtice, to exceed the meaſure of his mercy, leaſt we bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in his wrath, and brought to nothing in his heauy diſpleaſure. Spare vs good Lord, ſpare vs we beſeech thee, <hi>For the graue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confeſſe thee, the dead cannot praiſe thee, but the liuing, yea the liuing ſhall glorifie thy name in the multitude of thy mercies:</hi> as we doe this day, yealding vnto thy glorious Maieſty, all power, praiſe, glory, and thankeſgiuing, the reſt of this day and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
